<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of worshipping the Holy Ghost expressly, as a person equal to, and distinct from the Father</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27569</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355611</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205946</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248550871</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O144B</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">31355611</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of worshipping the Holy Ghost expressly, as a person equal to, and distinct from the Father</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Trinity --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Antitrinitarianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:205946:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205946:1"/>
            <head>Of Worshipping the <hi>HOLY GHOST</hi> expresly, as a Person equal to, and distinct from the <hi>FATHER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce the Doctrine of the Trinity, or of three equal Persons in one God, is not (as all confess) a Dictate of Nature or Reason, but is knowable or credible by means of Revelation only: and since all authentick Revelations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by Protestants are contained in Holy Scripture; and since the Proofs from Scripture of the Godhead of the Holy Ghost, are not direct and express, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequential, it follows, that even upon sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position that he is in some sense God, yet he is not to be worshipped any otherwise, than in the one Person of God, or the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, because there is neither Precept nor Example of any other Worship of him in Holy Scripture. But the whole Current of Scripture is for the Worship of God under that one Person of the Father, or God of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> Concerning the Worship of our Lord Christ I shall speak afterward.</p>
            <p>For if the Holy Scripture does not teach us, both under what Names and Notions, Appellations and Attributes, to worship God, then it is not a sufficient and clear Rule of Faith and Worship in all things necessary, (as those Names, Notions, Appellations and Attributes are) as all Protestants hold it is: And if there be neither Precept nor Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of worshipping God under the express Name, Notion or Appellation of Holy Ghost or Spirit, as a Person distinct from God the Father; but all Instances run in a contrary Stream, then such Worship is a humane Invention, introduced into the Worship of God, derogatory to his Honour, (whose Prerogative it is to appoint his own Worship) and to the Sufficiency and Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Scripture.</p>
            <p>For since the Holy Scripture is (as I have said) the only Revelation we have, that there is a Holy Ghost, and what he is, it's altogether necessary that we ascribe nothing to him, but what is ascribed to him in that Revelation.</p>
            <p>But here perhaps it will be asserted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what I deny, That though there is no Precept for worshipping God, under the Name and Notion of Holy Ghost, as distinct from the Father, yet there are some Texts of Scripture whence an Example of such Worship or Invocation may be drawn. For this they alledg, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 14. In the first of these Texts, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles are sent forth to baptize in [or into] the Name of the Holy Ghost, as well as of the Father and the Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I can see no shew of Adoration in that Scripture: forasmuch as to be baptized in, or into the Name of any One, and to be baptized into One, is the same thing, as the Learned agree; and is manifest by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. (where we read, <hi>Baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> [or unto] <hi>Jesus Christ</hi>) with <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Be Baptized every one of you in the Name of Jesus Christ.</hi> See the like use of these Phrases, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. with <hi>Acts</hi> 8.16. But the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites (as the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> says, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.) <hi>were all Baptized into</hi> [or unto] <hi>Moses, in the Cloud, and in the Sea.</hi> By which is not to be
<pb facs="tcp:205946:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205946:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:205946:3"/>understood, that they worshipped <hi>Moses</hi> with Divine Worship, but they were oblig'd to give heed to what he taught and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them in the Name of God the Lord. So to be Baptized into the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, is, as it's explain'd in the next words, to be taught, and obliged solemnly to observe all things whatsoever the Father hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Son, whom he anointed with the Holy Ghost and Power, or by those on whom the Son poured out the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, the Comforter or Advocate, and imports nothing of Adoration or Invocation.</p>
            <p>Besides, it's not unusual in Scripture to join other Persons with God, as one Object of the Action that respects them, when yet that Action respects God in one manner as Supream, and those other Persons in another manner as Subordinate. Thus the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites believed the Lord, and his Servant <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> [Marg. Heb. <hi>In the Lord, and in</hi> Moses <hi>his Servant</hi>], Exod. 14.31. <hi>The People great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feared the Lord, and</hi> Samuel, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18. —<hi>they cried, The Sword</hi> [not Swords] <hi>of the Lord, and of</hi> Gideon, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.20. So be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baptized into the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, does not respect each of them equally and in the same manner. For it's manifest, Believers were Baptized, that they might receive the Gift of the Holy Ghost; see <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</p>
            <p>The other Text in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. runs thus, <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Love of God, and the Communion of the Holy Ghost be with you all. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I answer; 1. That this Passage has the Form of a Wish, and not of a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. It's too obscurely form'd to bear the weight of an Instance of praying to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost: that Passage in <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. is far clearer for praying to the seven Spirits that are before the Throne, which yet Protestants deny to be any firm <hi>ground</hi> for our so doing. As for the <hi>Amen</hi> here read, <hi>Grotius</hi> says, It is not in that old Manuscript which he makes much use of; and that it was added by the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. The Holy Ghost is not here considered as God, for he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly distinguish'd from him. 3. Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> would read it <hi>Communication,</hi> as the same word in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <hi>The Communication of the Blood of Christ,</hi> that is, the Blood of Christ communicated; and so the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the Holy Spirit is, the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit communicated be, or abide with you all. I know not how it consists with Reverence to the one God or his Word, to ground the Worship of another Person as the most High God, besides and distinct from him that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is so, upon so obscure an Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion as this is: considering also that it has been in all Ages of Christianity the Custom of the Church to pray to the Father for the Communication of the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>There is another Text alledg'd by some, as an Instance of praying to the Holy Ghost, <hi>viz.</hi> Cant. 4.16. <hi>Awake thou North Wind, and come thou South, blow upon my Garden,</hi> &amp;c. which is so frivolous, that I shall not think it worthy of any Answer. I find also that the 6th of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> compar'd with <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25. is urged to the same purpose. Whence they collect, first, that the same Person who spake to <hi>Isaiah</hi> in Vision, <hi>v.</hi> 8. is the Lord; and <hi>v.</hi> 3. the Lord of Hosts; the same is by the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> said to be the Holy Ghost: and then it follows, that the same Holy Ghost is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Seraphims, saying, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> &amp;c. But the Answer is easy, for <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>Well spake the Holy Ghost by</hi> Isaiah <hi>the Prophet to our Fathers,</hi> [to wit, when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spir'd him in speaking or writing that Vision to the People] whereas God spake to <hi>Isaiah</hi> in the Vision: and so for different Reasons the same words are attributed both to God and to the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>But now it will be vehemently urg'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, That the Holy Scripture revealing the Holy Ghost to be God, and that he is one of those three Persons, who are each of them distinctly God, and all of them one God, it's necessary in Reason, and by natural Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that he ought to be worshipped un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Name, Notion and Distinction.</p>
            <p>I answer, and deny that Consequence, for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205946:3"/>these Reasons. 1. Because we ought not to carry a pure Revelation by our Reasonings, (which are very fallacious) beyond the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that Revelation; and we ought to measure the Extent of it by the Revelation it self, for otherwise we should readily run into many and great Errors, Superstitions and Contests, as by lamentable Experience is too too manifest by the Controversies among Christians, especially with Papists. But to go no further than the Case in hand: If all the Worship due to God upon any Account, and which we give to the Father because he is so, by the Name of the Father, be also due to the Holy Ghost expresly, because he is God, by the Name and Notion of Holy Ghost, as well as the Father, because, as the <hi>Athanasian Creed</hi> says, <hi>We must give them equal Glory;</hi> we shall be obliged to transprose, add to, and alter Scripture, and make it contradict it self in a thousand places; particularly, every time we use the Lord's Prayer, and in all Prayers, Praises and Adorations we make after that Pattern, instead of <hi>OƲR Father which art in Heaven,</hi> we must say, Our Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, which are in Heaven; and instead of <hi>Hallowed be THY Name,</hi> Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be YOUR Name; <hi>THY Kingdom come,</hi> we must say, in consequence of our reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, YOUR Kingdom come; and so not THY Will, but YOUR Will be done; not THINE is the Kingdom, but YOURS is the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So when we worship, as the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> Ephes. 1.3. we must not say, <hi>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> but, <hi>Blessed be God, the Father, Son and Holy Ghost, the God and Father of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</hi> And so every where we must turn the Names of Father, God, Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into Father, Son, and Holy Ghost; <hi>Thou</hi> and <hi>Thee</hi> into <hi>Ye</hi> and <hi>You, Thine</hi> into <hi>Your,</hi> &amp;c. Thus making Holy Scripture a most unintelligible and absurd Book, or at least such as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists would have it, and nothing less than what Protestants hold it, the clear and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Revelation of the Mind of God; and the New Covenant, wherein is promised—<hi>all shall know me, from the least to the greatest,</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more difficult than the old.</p>
            <p>My second Reason why I deny that the Holy Ghost, supposing him to be God, is to be worshipped expresly as the Father, by virtue of our reasoning upon that Suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is drawn from the Reflection thereby cast upon all Holy Worshippers we read of in the Bible. For if the Holy Ghost be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the most High God, he was so from Eternity, and had from the beginning of the Creation an equal right of being worshipped in as express a manner as the Father or <hi>Jeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah;</hi> but we find no Footsteps of any such Worship, wherein the Holy Ghost was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly worshipped, but <hi>Jehovah</hi> is always worshipp'd under such Names, Descriptions, Appellations and Pronouns, as import ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly one singular Person or personal God. And by him the Patriarchs, Prophets and Jews did understand and signify the Creator of Heaven and Earth alone, the God of <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> and Christians understood the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, and not the Person of the Holy Ghost, any otherwise than as implied. Yea and our Lord Jesus himself, whenever he pray'd or worshipp'd God, did it under the Names, Notions and Descriptions which signify the Father, and in the singular Number; conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all the Patriarchs, Prophets and Jews until Christ, and all the Believers in Christ, and Christ himself too, (which is Blasphemy to suppose) erred in their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping God, making no express mention of the Holy Ghost, if it be a good Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from the Holy Ghost his being revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be a Person of God, that we ought to worship him distinctly under that Name, or some other peculiar to him. For it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, not only that we <hi>may,</hi> but that we <hi>must</hi> so worship him; for he that is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God as the Father, has, according to our Reasoning, as much right as he to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipp'd and invocated expresly, and cannot be denied it by us without Transgression. But the Holy Ghost himself, the Inspirer of Holy Scripture, doth never dictate any such express Worship of himself; and therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205946:4"/>the Argument in the Objection reflects high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon him, as negligent of the Glory of God, even his own Self, and the greatest, not only Defectiveness, but Impiousness (pardon the word) upon the Holy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which never teach the due and whole Worship of God, but only a part of it.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be held, that supposing the Holy Ghost to be a Person of God, he was always worshipp'd and invocated under the Name of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Lord God of Hosts,</hi> and the like: And in the Times of the New Covenant, under the Name of the <hi>Father, The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, The Father of Mercies,</hi> &amp;c. but never, either under the Old or New-Covenant-Times, by the Name of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> or <hi>God the Holy Ghost,</hi> or <hi>blessed Spirit of God,</hi> or any such Name as distinguishes him expresly from God the Father: Therefore such wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of him now is utterly unlawful, as reflecting Imperfection and Obscurity upon Holy Scripture, Error or Negligence upon all the Holy Men, Patriarchs, Prophets &amp; Apostles we read of in Scripture; yea (which is not to be thought or said, did not the detection of a great Error enforce it) upon our Lord Jesus the Pattern of Perfection, and upon the Holy Ghost himself, by whose Inspiration the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were written, and holy Men moved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Worship of the Holy Ghost, in such an express manner as distinguish'd from the Father, does naturally beget in us the Notion or Idea of two Persons with two Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sences, as fully as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> are two Essences: neither do I think it possible to avoid it, for I cannot make either the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the Holy Ghost, an Object of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship as the most High God, but I must no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion each of them distinctly as a Person and Essence compleat, and then of necessity I form in my Mind two Essences as well as two Persons, or else I worship the Essence twice under two different Persons: But whether the one or the other, I do expresly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship two most High Gods equal one to the other, whilst I have two such Objects under two different Names and Appellations, which signify as differently as Father and not Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but one equal to him.</p>
            <p>And now that I have shew'd, there is no Example, as well as no Precept, of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping or praying to the Holy Ghost by that Name, or any other Name or Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, signifying him as a Person distinct from the Father; and that such Worship is not to be justified by any Consequence drawn by our Reasoning from the Revelation of his being a Person of God; Yea, that it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful so to do, I first turn my self to the Dissenters, and charge them with great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistency to themselves and their own Principles; for whilst they refuse to join in the Liturgy and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> because (say they) there is neither Precept nor Example in Scripture for such a Liturgy or Ceremonies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject all the Reasons the Church-men draw from Order and Decency, the Command of Superiours in Matters of Indifferency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they themselves do daily worship, and that expresly by Names and Appellations, which infer different Idea's and Notions, a Person distinct from the Father, the only true God, without any Warrant of Scripture, either by Precept, or so much as one Example; nay, against the full current of Scripture-worship, with heinous reflection upon all holy Worshippers, yea, upon our Lord Christ and the Holy Ghost himself, and the unavoidable danger (in all the common People at least) of worshipping two Gods. Thus you can no longer plead the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Principle, that the Scriptures are a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, clear, and our only Rule of Faith and Worship; and that nothing is lawful in the Worship of God, but what he hath either commanded or exemplified. You must not call the Liturgy and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Will-worship, whilst your selves are Will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers in the very Essence, Object and Form of Worship. Instead of one Person which God commands you to worship, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thou shalt have no other Gods before ME,</hi> you have in daily practice chang'd ME into US, one into two Persons expresly. You
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205946:4"/>must not henceforth draw a Parallel between <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s worshipping the God of <hi>Israel</hi> by Calves, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God in consecrated Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, Cathedrals, Priests Garments, by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Liturgies, singing Service, Litanies, Bowings, Crossings, Holidays, Fasts, Feasts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> because all these, and a great deal more, may be justified better than you can justify worshipping God by those express Names and Descriptions that make him plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and not the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ only; and that without any Authority, but merely of your own Heads. And this unscriptural Worship is so frequent with you, that you seldom make two Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but one or both of them is concluded with the Worship of the Holy Ghost ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, together with the Father and the Son. Nay, you are so addicted to this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of your own Invention, or rather Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, that though there are many Forms of Worship and Doxology in Scripture, especially in the New Testament, for New-Covenant Worshippers, yet you seldom make use of any of them, but neglect them all, preferring your Popish Invention before them.</p>
            <p>Particularly you Baptists, or Anabaptists, do worthily labour in the vindicating of Baptism to those that are capable of it, from those that are uncapable of it, whilst in the mean time you follow the most cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Tradition, of giving the Glory due to the one Person of God only, to another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son as his Equal.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, I crave leave to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress my self to the Church-men, (who are so frequently bragging of the purity of their Faith and Worship) and put them also in mind of their dishonouring God in this Point, whilst every Morning they read their Liturgy, they repeat Pope <hi>Damasus</hi>'s Doxology, at least seven, for the most part eight or nine times, sometimes fourteen or fifteen times, <hi>viz. Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost: As it was in the Beginning,</hi> &amp;c. For the Learned in Antiquities tell us, that this Doxology was first devis'd to be the Cognizance of a Faction, and did produce tragical Riots and Tumults; then in the Year 376, it was taken into the Church-Service by Bishop <hi>Damasus,</hi> who was brought into that Office at <hi>Rome,</hi> by Tumult and Slaughter of above one hundred <hi>Roman</hi> Citizens. Now is not this a high Pedigree of a Form of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, that must thrust out, and be preferr'd before all those excellent Doxologies and Thanksgivings in Holy Scripture, inspir'd by the Holy Ghost. Such are these;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the King Eternal, Immortal, Invisible, the only wise God, be Honour and Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p>THere is a like Description of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15, 16.—<hi>the blessed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; Who only hath Immortality, dwelling in the Light which no Man can approach unto, whom no Man hath seen, nor can see; to whom be Honour and Power everlasting.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Another in <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 25. <hi>To the only wise God our Saviour, be Glory and Majesty, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Power, both now and for ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>To God only Wise, be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, through Jesus Christ for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.5. <hi>To whom</hi> [God and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther] <hi>be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Now to him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the Power that worketh in us; unto him be Glory in the Church by Christ Jesus, throughout all Ages, World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Phil. 4.20. <hi>Now unto God and our Father be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>1 Pet. 5.10, 11. To—<hi>the God of all Grace, who hath called us to his eternal Glory by Christ Jesus—to him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>2 Pet. 3.18. <hi>To our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, be Glory both now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205946:5"/>
            <p>Rev. 4.11. <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power; for thou hast created all things, and for thy Pleasure they are and were created.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. 5.12. <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was slain, to receive Power, and Riches, and Wisdon, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> Ver. 13. <hi>Blessing, and Honour, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Power, be to him that sitteth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See also 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Blessed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of Mercies, and the God of all Comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> So also <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.3. Thanksgivings are commonly rendred to God through Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>Now, Reverend Sirs, is it not unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that a Person equal to this God and Father, and who has an equal Right to all Glory and Honour, should never be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned? And, is it not as unaccountable, that a Church professing a most exact Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation from Popish Traditions, in Faith and Worship, by the only Rule of Holy Scripture, should thus palpably derogate from Scripture, to the high dishonour of all sacred Persons and Things; and give your Adversaries the Romanists an Argument and Advantage, whereby they are able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the very worst of their Superstitions and Idolatries, and subvert your only Rule of Faith? If these Doxologies had not been found in Scripture, but devised by some eminent Bishop or Patriarch, you would certainly have counted it a great disrespect to that Bishop to pass them by, and take one devised by an ordinary weak Man of no Reputation, (supposing the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it to have been lawful); But what is Pope <hi>Damasus</hi> in compare with the Holy Ghost, or even with the Apostles and Holy Penmen? You must no longer reject the Popish <hi>Worship of Saints and Angels, the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Christ and his Mother, and other Saints; the Bread in Transubstantiation,</hi> &amp;c. because not found in Scripture, our only Rule of Faith and Worship; neither a thousand more of their Doctrines, Ceremonies and Usages, whilst you constantly every day, and often in every day repeat the Worship of another Person expresly, besides and in distinction from him that is the supream God, and together with him, whereby you cast great Contempt upon Holy Scripture, as an imperfect and defective Rule of Faith and Worship, even in the most Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Point, the highest Object of Worship. The Papists are not wanting of Reasonings, Arguments, Consequences, for what they believe and practise in Religion: but you reject them because not found in Scripture. See what your most learned Defender says, in his Discourse of the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> pag. 175. §. 16. <q rend="margQuotes">And so <hi>(saith be)</hi> for all particular Doctrines rejected by us — We therefore refuse the belief of them, because not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained IN OUR ONLY RULE OF FAITH: on this account we reject the Pope's Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, Transubstantiation, Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the present Church in delivering Points of Faith, Purgatory, and other Fopperies, impos'd upon the Belief of Christians.</q> Thus far he.</p>
            <p>But in contradiction to this Principle, you believe it acceptable to God the Father, to worship expresly another equal to him: you can profess to believe that unscriptural, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible and damning Creed of your Saint <hi>Athanasius,</hi> whereby you damn all that do not give equal Glory to the Holy Ghost as to the Father; and consequently your selves, for ye often pray to, and worship the Father expresly without mention of the Holy Ghost, nay, ye pray to the Father that he would give you the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>Thus far I have discoursed mostly upon that Protestant Principle named above; but now I will shew you that that your Faith and Worship is directly contrary to the <hi>Precepts</hi> of Worship in holy Scripture, and that not one only, but all of them. For all the Precepts as well as Examples concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Worship of God, respect him as one singular Person, both in Essence and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205946:5"/>Person; for there can be no Person with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Essence, and one Almighty and most wise Person is one most High God: All Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of worshipping that God speak in the singular number o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one such Person, and exclude every other Person whatsoever; and therefore even the Person of the Holy Ghost, considered as a distinct Person from the Father, and so exprest; for being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest with the Father, they make two Gods, and then our Blessed Saviour could not with Congruity to Truth and Grammar, have expounded that Precept of God by <hi>Moses [Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and serve him]</hi> thus; <hi>It is written, Thou shalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the Lord thy God, and HIM only shalt thou serve,</hi> Mat. 4.10. for he that worships the Father alone expresly, worships the Lord his God; and he that worships ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly another Person besides him with equal Worship, worships no longer the Lord his God, and serves <hi>him only,</hi> but he worships the Lord his God and another, and serves THEM together; so our Lord's Precept and Form of Prayer directs to one singular Person, as I have shewed above, <hi>p.</hi> 3. And being asked, <hi>which is the first Commandment of all? Jesus answered him, The first of all the Commandments is, Hear O</hi> Israel, <hi>the Lord our God is one Lord,</hi> [or the Lord our God the Lord is one.] <hi>And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind, and with all thy Strength:</hi> Where he makes the Oneness of the Person of God the very ground of all that Love, Worship and Service which we are able to perform, and which we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to one Person only; <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.29, 30. with <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4, 5. I think I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in any more. But you elude all Divine Precepts of Worship, and make them of none effect by your Tradition; for you have received a Litany from Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> I. which teaches you to pray, <hi>O holy, and blessed, and glorious Trinity, three Persons and one God, have Mercy upon us. O God the Father of Heaven, O God the Son, O God the Holy Ghost proceeding from the Father and the Son, have Mercy upon us.</hi> So you change the Lord our God his great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, repeated by the Mouth of our Saviour, into the quite contrary, <hi>him only</hi> into <hi>them,</hi> and the God that is <hi>one</hi> you make <hi>three,</hi> and serve <hi>them</hi> with equal Worship. And instead of that Doxology which our Lord taught us to form our Doxologies by, you have introduced this or the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of <hi>Gregory</hi> and other Popes in above twenty Collects and Prayers, namely,— <hi>him</hi> [Jesus Christ] <hi>who liveth and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghost now and ever;</hi> first Collect in <hi>Advent,</hi> and in the third Collect thus—<hi>O Lord Jesus Christ — who livest and reignest with the Father and the Holy Spirit, ever one God, World without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>But after all, it will be urg'd against me, that our Lord Jesus is often worshipp'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelly together with the Father; and if he, why not also the Holy Ghost? To which I answer: 1. That there is a far different Consideration of Christ and of the Holy Ghost; for the Holy Ghost has no other Consideration in the Worship done to him, but that of God, or a Person that is God; but Jesus Christ has the Consideration of <hi>the well-beloved Son of God, whom he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Heir of all things, by whom also he made the Worlds, whom he sanctified and sent into the World; whom, because he humbled himself, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Cross, God hath highly exalted, and given him a Name above every Name, that at [or in] the Name of Jesus every Knee should bow, and that every Tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the Glory of God the Father;</hi> but no such thing can be said or thought of the Holy Ghost, who whatsoever Worship is paid to him, it redounds ultimately to his own Glory in Distinction from God the Father, and in Equality with him. All the express Worship to be exhibited to Christ, has this Ground and Foundation, namely, that the Father, even God, has given him that Power, Authority and Dominion which makes him a fit Object of that Worship,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205946:6"/>and the Glory thereof is not terminated in him as in its utmost scope, but passes by and through him to the Father. Both these Considerations are clear and apparent in that Passage to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> which I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and so in the Discourse of our Lord himself, <hi>John</hi> 5. for when the Jews who <hi>sought to kill him,</hi> v. 18. did maliciously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret his saying, that God was his Father, to be a making himself equal with God, he denies with a solemn Asseveration, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Verily, verily, the Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father do; for what things soever he doth, these also doth the Son likewise.</hi> And how comes that to pass? <hi>For the Father loveth the Son, and sheweth him all things that himself doth,</hi> (ver. 20.) <hi>and he will shew him greater Works than these, that ye may marvel.</hi> It was such a shewing which proceeded from the Love of the Father; and it was partly present, and partly future. <hi>For as the Father raiseth the Dead, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, even so the Son quickneth whom he will,</hi> ver. 21. This is one of those Works which the Father shews him. <hi>For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgeth no Man, but hath committed all Judgment to the Son, that all Men should ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Son even as they honour the Father:</hi> To wit, as they honour the Father upon the account of his judging; but doth this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour terminate in the Son? No, <hi>he that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth not the Son, honoureth not the Father that sent him.</hi> That Honour which is given to the Son, ascends by him as sent to the Father that sent him, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath Life in himself, so hath he given to the Son to have Life in himself; and hath given him Authority to execute Judgment also, because he is the Son of Man,</hi> that is, he that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied of in the Visions of <hi>Daniel,</hi> where we read, that <hi>one like the Son of Man— came to the Ancient of Days, and they brought him near before him, and there was given him Dominion, and Glory, and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Languages should serve him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 13, 14. or because he is such a Son of Man as humbles himself to the meanest and hardest Condition of the most ordinary Man: See <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7, 8. Again, in <hi>ver.</hi> 30. of this of <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. <hi>I can of my self do nothing; as I hear, I judg, and my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is just.</hi> Why, because he is the most High God? No, but <hi>because I seek not mine own Will, but the Will of the Father which hath sent me.</hi> These Reasons of Worship agree to a Man exalted by God, but by no means to him that is himself God already. Can he that is God the most high be made Higher than he is? God may and ought to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and praised for those Excellencies that are in him; but he can have no Addition to his natural and inherent Power, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Glory. But the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> also tells the People in that famous Sermon, Acts 2.36. — <hi>Let all the House of</hi> Israel <hi>know assuredly, that God hath made that same Jesus whom ye have crucified both Lord and Christ.</hi> And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. <hi>For to this end Christ both died, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living.</hi> Hence it is that in the Visions of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> chap. 5. where the twenty four Elders fall down before the <hi>Lamb, and sing a new Song,</hi> they exhibit that Worship to him, they do it not upon the account of his being the most High God, but upon account of his Worthiness as a Man, saying, <hi>Thou art worthy—because thou wast slain, and hast redeemed us to God by thy Blood out of every Tribe, and Tongue, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Nation, and hast made us to our God Kings and Priests,</hi> ver. 9, 10. So by the Angels, Animals, Elders, even thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of thousands, Christ is celebrated upon the same account of his being the Lamb that was slain, saying, <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was slain, to receive Power, and Riches, and Wisdom, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Blessing,</hi> ver. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>This Observation of mine, touching the different Ground of the Worship of Christ from that of the Worship of the Father, or of the Holy Ghost (who are alway wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipp'd as Persons of the most High God) is so firm, that I am perswaded there is no place of Scripture can be alledged of any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205946:6"/>Divine Excellency attributed to Christ, but it will plainly appear to have been given him by the Father, out of his free Love, or as a Reward of his Obedience. Thus in <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. where all things in Heaven and in Earth [not Heaven and Earth] are said to be created by Christ; he is said there to be, <hi>The Image of the Invisible God, the First-born of every Creature,</hi> vers. 15. He forgave Sins, but as the Son of Man empowred by God so to do, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.6, 7. And the Apostles tell the High Priest and Council, saying, <hi>The God of our Fathers has raised up Jesus, whom ye slew and hanged on a Tree: Him hath God exalted with his right Hand, to be a Prince and a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to give Repentance to</hi> Israel, <hi>and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of Sins,</hi> Acts 5.30, 31. Christ is to be believed on, but so, as that he <hi>who believeth on him, believeth not on him, but on another;</hi> to wit, <hi>on him that sent him,</hi> John 12.44. And so, that by and <hi>through him we believe in God, who raised him from the Dead, and gave him Glory,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.21. He hath the Name of <hi>Emmanuel</hi> (God with us) given to him; yet he is so a God, that when he is so called, he also is said to have a God who anointed him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8, 9. He is said to be <hi>the First and the Last,</hi> Rev. 1.17. but so as <hi>he that liveth and was dead,</hi> ver. 18. He hath the Name of <hi>The Lord our Righteousness,</hi> Jer. 23.5, 6. (if at least that Appellation doth not agree to <hi>Israel</hi> mentioned before) but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is common to him with <hi>Israel,</hi> Jer. 33.16. God only searcheth the Heart pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, and of himself; but he can give to others an Ability to search the Heart, as to <hi>Elisha,</hi> 2 Kings 8.12. So Christ saith, <hi>I am he which searcheth the Reins and Heart:</hi> But he speaketh there of a Revelation which God gave unto him, and of himself as executing Judgment upon Adulterers, and giving to every one a Reward according to his Works. But it is certain that Christ as a Man is Judg, as I observ'd before from <hi>John</hi> 5.27. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> saith, That God <hi>shall judg the World in Righteousness, by that MAN whom he hath ordained,</hi> Acts 17.31.</p>
            <p>My Conclusion from all is, That all the Worship that is or ought to be exhibited to Christ, according to Holy Scripture, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd upon him as a Man, Mediator between God and Men; and that neither to Him nor to the Holy Ghost, there ever was any Worship given under any express Names, Appellations or Descriptions, as Persons of God distinct from God the Father. But, supposing them to have been from Eternity such Persons, they were always worshipp'd as implied in God the Father; and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Argument in the Objection, for the Worship of the Holy Spirit expresly, because Christ is worshipp'd expresly, is of no force.</p>
            <p>My second Answer to the same Objection is this: I observed above, that other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are sometimes joined with God the Father, as Objects of some great Work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, or some Honour given by Men, when yet that Work or Honour respects Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in one manner, and those other Persons in another manner; as in the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites believing in the Lord and in <hi>Moses;</hi> the People fearing the Lord and <hi>Samuel; Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi>'s Army, <hi>crying, The Sword of the Lord, and of</hi> Gideon. I now add 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 29.20. where it is said, <hi>All the Congregation blessed the Lord God of their Fathers, and bowed down their Heads, and worshipped the Lord and the King.</hi> So it is when Christ is worshipped with the Father, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. he is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced (as I shewed) from him that sitteth upon the Throne, by the Appellation of <hi>the Lamb that was slain, and had redeemed us to God by his Blood.</hi> But as for the Holy Ghost, as he is not considered in the Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given to him under any other Notion than of God, or a Person of God, so your Liturgy respects him in the same manner, and in coequality with God the Father; not as Christ, who received from the Bounty of his Father, that Power for which he is to be honoured and obeyed. Thus the <hi>eleven Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> after his Resurrection, and at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from them, <hi>worshipped him.</hi> Matth. 28.17. <hi>And Jesus came, and spake unto them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205946:7"/>saying, All Power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth: Go ye THEREFORE and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> This Scripture is chiefly urged as a Proof of three equal Almighty and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Persons in God: But the inequality of the Son to the Father is most evident, in that the Son saith immediately before, <hi>That all Power was given to him;</hi> and lays the Authority of this great and extensive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of so making Disciples, baptizing them, upon that Donation: which is the more observable, because it is the custom of all Princes, built upon most weighty Reason, that when they send out extraordinary Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors, they enforce their Authority with the best and highest of their Titles and Powers: consequently this, of having all Power given to him, was our Lord Jesus's highest Title. And then it's preposterous to imagine, that the Holy Ghost who is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd after him, should have a higher Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, to wit, of a personal God: But if he have not that, you will acknowledg that no Adoration is due to him.</p>
            <p>And now I know how strong a Prejudice both the Church-men and Dissenters in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral have against this Discourse: So strong, that it may be doubted, whether many of them will give it the reading; and of those that will, very few will take any considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Reasons I have alledg'd against this inveterate practice of worshipping ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly the Holy Ghost: And of those few, it will be as hard to find one that will give my Arguments their due weight, as it is to find a Papist that will be convinced of the Absurdities of Transubstantiation, or the Dishonour done to God in worshipping the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and other Saints, and their dead Images. So loth is every one to judg himself to have been in an Error, especially in so gross an one as is the religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of a false Object; and more yet, when we have the concurrence of the Multitude of Learned and Unlearned on our side. But those that will be sincere in the study of Religion, (as all must that shall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Life) ought to consider that many Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions crept into the Christian Church very early, as every one that is but a little acquainted with Antiquity, knows. And the fourth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> which was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated about the end of the fourth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, seems to have judg'd this worshipping of the Holy Ghost an Innovation, when it decreed thus; <hi>Cum ad altare assistitur,</hi> &amp;c. Which may be Englished, <hi>In the Church let Prayer be made to God by only the Name of the Father.</hi> And there are not wanting Learned Authors who tell us, It was several hundreds of Years before the Publick Prayers had in them any Prayer to the Holy Ghost: Of which thing the Commentators on the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Rituals of the Church; give this remarkable Reason, <hi>Quia S. Spiritus, Because the Holy Spirit is the Gift, not the Giver.</hi> And <hi>Erasmus</hi> and others observe, that St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> who wrote twelve Books of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> never call'd the Holy Ghost <hi>God,</hi> never said that he was to be worshipped, but only to be obtain'd. And Dr. <hi>Sparks</hi> on the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy acknowledges, that the Doxology so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reiterated in the Common Prayer; did formerly run thus, <hi>Glory be to the Father, through the Son, and by the Holy Ghost. We worship</hi> (says <hi>Origen,</hi> contra Celsum) <hi>the one only God; and his one only Son, and Word and Similitude, with our utmost Supplications and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, bringing our Prayers to the God of all things, through his only begotten Son.</hi> Here's no mention of the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> were devoured by Fire from the Lord, for offering strange Fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him which he commanded them not; who shall not dread to worship even another Almighty Person equal to him, which he has so strictly forbidden? The Times of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance God winks at; but when his Mind is clearly made known, then he commands all Men every where to repent.</p>
            <p>I remember that a most eminent and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Conformist</hi> Preacher of <hi>London,</hi> (whose Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals were worthily solemniz'd with Tears and Elegies) about thirty Years ago, did, upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205946:7"/>the account of the Reflection upon the Holy Scriptures, and the Scandal given to some of his Hearers, by that Doxology I have been speaking of, did, I say, forbear to use it as long as he lived. A rare Example! But how contrary is the Spirit that now reigns among our Clergy, who make use of this Doxology as the very Mark of Orthodoxy; and will at no time forbear it, especially if they find any Person in the Congregation that is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with it.</p>
            <p>You ought to remember, the Popish Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors had prevail'd long, when the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers began; yea, some of them longer than your Adoration of the Holy Ghost: And it was esteem'd as horrid an Heresy to deny the Adoration of the Host, as of the Holy Ghost; and those that reform'd in that Point, were as few in Number as we that reform in this. Why should you think you have reform'd all the Errors of so corrupt a Church, or that her Antichristia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism consists only in those things that you have reform'd? Remember, that the most High God proclaims himself jealous in no Commandment but that of his Worship; and try again whether you give him no cause to be so: See if you can satisfy your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences in these Adorations; be so kind and Christian, as to inform us how we may satisfy ours. If you cannot satisfy us who are ready to receive Satisfaction, then you ought to allow our Dissent and Separation from your Worship. In the mean time it will be our Duty to profess our Thankfulness to God through Christ, who has bestowed so great a Benefit upon us, as to deliver us from so great an Error, whereby we were confounded in the Worship of God, and in reading and understanding of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. O thou God and Father, strengthen us to walk worthy of so great a Blessing!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>HAving spoken of the Unlawfulness, and consequently the Danger of worshipping the Holy Ghost ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, it may not be unseasonable to repeat that important Query, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the Faith and Worship of Three Almighty and only Wise Persons, or of one only, to wit, The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, be most dangerous to the Souls of Men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Trinitarians and Unitarians agree, that there is but one God most High: they both agree that the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, is that most High God. They differ in this, that Jesus before he was a Man, and from Eternity, and also the Holy Ghost, as distinct Persons from God the Father, were and are each of them as as perfectly God most High, as the Father; so that each of them is Almighty, Eternal, All-knowing, only Wise, only Good, Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> equal to the Father. The Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians assert these things, the Unitarians deny them.</p>
            <p>The Question hereupon is, Which of these Parties are in the most dangerous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, supposing them to be in Error, now the one, now the other?</p>
            <p>If the Trinitarians err, they worship two Persons in God equal to one who is undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly God; that is, they worship three Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and only Wise Persons, which are not distinguishable (especially in Worship) from three most High Gods.</p>
            <p>If the Unitarians err, they avoid that Error of worshipping three Persons, which they cannot distinguish from three Gods; but their Error lies in holding so strictly to the Oneness of God, as well in Person as Essence, that they do not acknowledg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205946:8"/>that One, two more Persons to be equally God, as well as that One, whom both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties agree to be so: that is, they err in not worshipping two unnecessary Persons in God, but holding that the God and Father of Christ is God alone, only Necessary and All-sufficient.</p>
            <p>If the Trinitarians err, they err against the common Reason of Mankind, and most plain and express Scriptures, which assert that God is One, or that there is but one most High God, or God of Gods, and throughout speak of him as of one only Person. If the Unitarians err, they err against the doubtful Sense of some obscure Texts, which are either variously read in the Hebrew and Greek, or not rightly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated, or which fairly admit of another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation consistent with the Unity of the Person of God.</p>
            <p>In short, the Question is, Whether the Term <hi>God</hi> includes only one Person, or three Persons? One Almighty Person, or three distinct Almighty Persons? And whether the former or the latter is the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Error, which soever is found an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror?</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 23.24.</hi>
                  </bibl> Ye blind Guides, which strain at a Gnat, and swallow a Camel.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 9.40.</hi>
                  </bibl> And some of the Pharisees — said unto him, Are we blind also?</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:205946:8"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>